Ruth Mellor Papers, 1921-1970
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Ruth Mellor Papers
1921-1970
1928-1930
Mellor, Ruth
MS 253
2 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Social Worker. Papers consist primarily of material related to a survey conducted by Ruth Mellor in 1929 for the Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene to assess social welfare services in the state of Connecticut. Also included is personal correspondence with close friend and Smith College classmate, Mildred Scott Olmsted and numerous love letters to Mellor from both a woman and man.
Biographical Note
Ruth Mellor was born in Rockville, Connecticut on January 15, 1889 and graduated from Smith College in 1912. In 1916-17, she attended the Bryant and Stratton Business School in Boston, and from 1918 to 1922 was executive secretary of American Red Cross, Plymouth, Massachusetts. In 1923 she earned her master's degree in psychiatric social work at the School of Social Work in New York City, afterwards working as Chief of Social Service at the Child Guidance Demonstration Clinic in Cleveland, Ohio, from 1924 to 1926. From 1926 to 1929 she worked at the Children's Aid Society in Philadelphia, taking time in 1929 to act as field psychiatric worker in a survey conducted by the Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene. While living in the Philadelphia area, she continued her friendship with Mildred Scott Olmsted, who also graduated from Smith College in 1912. Mellor worked as a social worker for the Massachusetts Society for Mental Hygiene from 1929 to 1931, and from 1931 to 1933 was executive secretary of the Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene. She took a position as executive director of the Mental Hygiene Clinic in Louisville, Kentucky, where she remained at least until 1949. (This clinic was renamed the Bingham Child Guidance Clinic, which was heir to Ruth Mellor's estate.) She was also a lecturer in the Social Sciences division of the Department of Psychiatry at the University of Louisville until her retirement in 1961. She died in Louisville on November 9, 1989.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The papers consist primarily of material related to a survey conducted by Ruth Mellor in 1929 for the Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene. The purpose of the survey was to assess social welfare services in the state of Connecticut, and information was gathered from institutions concerned with providing those services. They included churches; hospitals and clinics; mental health institutions; state agencies; charities and humane societies; and county homes, as well as rural and city schools and several colleges. The principle method for gathering information was to interview a range of educators, judges, lawmakers, doctors, social workers, prison wardens, and other citizens concerned with the welfare of the indigent and the mentally, emotionally and physically impaired. The interviews are summarized by Mellor and often include her frank assessment of the interviewee. These, along with some statistical data and notations about site visits, comprise the bulk of the papers. Mellor often used the reverse side of professional correspondence for hand-written and typed notes.
Also included are twenty-seven passionate love letters to Mellor from Marion W. Bomer, called Maisie or Wendy, written in 1928-29. Apparently against Bomer's wishes and to her distress, Mellor had insisted on one year of separation, during which time Bomer pined for her and pleaded to be reunited. The letters clearly indicate a lesbian relationship. The papers also include letters to Bomer from two other women who appear to have been attracted to her romantically. Love letters to Mellor from George de Schweinitz, written during the 1930s, suggest that Mellor was probably bi-sexual.
The papers also include general correspondence, and typed and hand-written notes. Material pertaining to Mellor's education is located in the Professional Activities series, as part of her employment application to the Connecticut Society for Mental Health. Since Dr. Samuel W. Hamilton participated in the Connecticut Society for Mental Health survey, a list of interviews by him is filed with those conducted by Mellor.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical
II. Correspondence
III. Professional Activities
IV. Subjects
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Swarthmore Peace Collection donated the Ruth Mellor Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1991. The Bingham Child Guidance Center donated additional material in 1999.
Search Terms
Mental health facilities--Connecticut--History--20th century--Sources; Social workers--United States--History--Sources; Mellor, Ruth; Olmsted, Mildred Scott, 1890-1990; Ackerly, Spafford; Bingham Child Guidance Center--History; Female friendship--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Bisexuality--United States--History--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
The Ruth Mellor Papers were originally part of the Mildred Scott Olmsted Papers at the Swarthmore Peace Collection, and additional correspondence is located there.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL
  - Expense book and notebook, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Travel correspondence and itineraries, 1927, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph, biographical data, clippings, funeral instructions, 1948-60, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Retirement, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2b)
  - Financial information, 1954-60, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2c)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - General, 1921-70, n.d. (Box 3-8)
  - From Marion W. "Maisie" Bomer, 1928-29, n.d. (Box 9)
  - From Sylvia [?], 1928-29, n.d. (Box 10)
  - From de George L. Schweinitz, 1933-39, n.d. (Box 11)
- SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene Survey
    - Administrative records
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1928-29 (Box 11, Folder 12)
        - From Samuel W. Hamilton to Ruth Mellor, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - General information about Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 14-15)
      - Minutes of survey committee meeting, 11 Jun 1929 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - Survey prospectus, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - Ruth Mellor, references and credentials submitted in application for survey position, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Expense sheets, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Interviews and statistical data
      - Bureau of Child Welfare, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Bureau of Special Education and Standards, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Charities and humane societies, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Churches, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Clinics, 1929
        - Bridgeport (Box 2, Folder 24)
          [See also Oversize Materials]
        - Bristol (Box 2, Folder 25)
        - Connecticut State Hospital (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - Hartley-Salmon (Box 2, Folder 27)
        - New Haven (Box 2, Folder 28)
        - Norwich (Box 2, Folder 29)
        - Waterbury (Box 2, Folder 30)
        - Unidentified clinic notes, 1927, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Colleges, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - County homes, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Courts, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Hospitals, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Industry, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Interviews with members of Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene, 1929, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Interviews with other concerned citizens, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Interviews by Samuel W. Hamilton (list), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Mental health institutions, city, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Mental health institutions, state, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Schools, city, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Schools, rural, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - State Department of Mental Health, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Survey forms, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Bingham Child Guidance Center
    - Correspondence
      - Ackerley, Spafford, 1933-61 (Box 2, Folder 45a)
    - Minutes and miscellaneous documents, 1953-58, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Professional affiliations, 1929, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
- SERIES IV. SUBJECTS
  - "Mental Hygiene Services in Out-Patient Departments of New York City," 1928-29 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "Philadelphia Health and Hospital Survey," n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified material, 1927-29, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Statistical charts for Connecticut Society for Mental Hygiene Survey, 1929 (Map-case Flat File:)